VSDS Mahesh Akavarapu

◆ Dept. of CSE, IITK, Kanpur, U.P., India☑ maheshak@cse.iitk.ac.in� cse.iitk.ac.in/users/maheshak

in mahesh-akavarapu • mahesh-

Research Interests _

Computational Linguistics / Natural Language Processing, Historical Linguistics

As part of my PhD thesis, I worked on Transformer and Graph-Attention-based architectures over the central problems in historical linguistics incorporating insights from Evolutionary Biology. Additionally, I worked on Phylogenetic testing of language families.

Education

PhD Indian Institute of Technology Kanpur, Computer Science

July 2019 to present

- GPA: 3.84/4.00 (9.6/10.0)
- · Advisor: Prof. Arnab Bhattacharya

BTech Indian Institute of Technology Kanpur, Computer Science, Physics (Second Maior)

July 2014 to May 2019

• GPA: 3.72/4.00 (9.3/10.0)

Awards / Honors _____

Prime Minister's Research Fellowship (2019-24): Grant of INR 200,000 per year (approx. USD 12,000 in total) from Ministry of Education, Government of India

Academic Excellence Award from IIT Kanpur (2015-16): Awarded to Top 10% students of the batch

Experience __

Indian Institute of Technology Kanpur, Research Fellow

• Under Prime Minister's Research Fellowship

Kanpur, India Aug. 2019 to July 2024 4 years 11 months

Indian Institute of Technology Kanpur, Student Researcher, Intern

• High Performance Computing in CUDA (Guide: Prof. Mahendra K. Verma)

Kanpur, India May 2018 to July 2018 2 months

Publications

A Likelihood Ratio Test of Genetic Relationship among Languages

June 2024

V.S.D.S.Mahesh Akavarapu, Arnab Bhattacharya

Accepted to NAACL 2024 (main), Mexico City, Mexico

Automated Cognate Detection as a Supervised Link Prediction Task with Cognate Transformer

Mar. 2024

V.S.D.S.Mahesh Akavarapu, Arnab Bhattacharya

Proc. of EACL 2024, St. Julian's, Malta

Cognate Transformer for Automated Phonological Reconstruction and Cognate Reflex Prediction

Dec. 2023

V.S.D.S.Mahesh Akavarapu, Arnab Bhattacharya

Proc. of EMNLP 2023, Singapore

Creation of a Digital Rig Vedic Index (Anukramani) for Computational Linguistic Tasks

V.S.D.S.Mahesh Akavarapu, Arnab Bhattacharya

Proc. of World Sanskrit Conference 2023, Canberra, Australia

Invited Talks ___

- Evolutionary Biology-Inspired Language Models in Historical Linguistics, University of Tübingen (Online), Apr. 2024
- Tutorial on LLMs: Finetuning and Prompting, with Arnab Bhattacharya and Shubham K. Nigam, NIT Warangal (Online), Mar. 2024
- Tutorial on Legal Named Entity Recognition, with Shubham K. Nigam, NIT Trichy (Online), Dec. 2022

Technologies _____

Languages: Python, C/C++, HTML, Shell Scripting etc.

Libraries: PyTorch, TensorFlow, HuggingFace, Pandas etc.